Guide to the New Almaden Mine (Calif.) Collection, 1845-1973
Department of Special Collections
New Almaden Mine (Calif.) Collection,
1845-1973
Special Collections M0270
New Almaden Mine (Calif.).
86 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Gift and purchase, Mrs. Phillips Schneider; gift of New Idria, Inc., 1976.
Historical Note
In 1845, Captain Andres Castillero of the Mexican Army was sent on a routine scouting patrol through what is now northern California, then part of Mexican territory. As an amateur geologist, Castillero recognized the possibility that the rolling hills held vast mineral deposits. During a visit to local Indians, his suspicions were confirmed. The Indians told him of the red rock they used to make paint, and of the cave where the walls were solid deposits of this red rock. A trip to the cave left Castillero amazed; the red rock was cinnabar, high grade mercury ore. He quickly filed a claim with the most suitable local authority, a justice of the peace, and received mineral rights to excavate the mine site. The rights were divided among five principal holders, including Castillero, his guide, and the Indians who led him to the mine.
Unfortunately for Castillero, Mexican land claim regulations were unusually complex, and he found that his claim to the mine could be disputed in court by anyone interested in filing their own claim. This consideration, along with orders from the Mexican Army to prepare for war with the United States, led Castillero to sell his rights to the mine to Barron, Forbes Company, an English industrial firm.
Barron, Forbes Company, which operated a cotton mill in Tepic, Mexico, soon acquired controlling interest in the mine by buying the shares of the other principals. Organized mining operations began at the renamed New Almaden Mines (after the famous Almaden quicksilver mine in Spain) in 1847. It was the first large-scale mining venture in California.
New Almaden proved to be a bonanza. Not only were there huge cinnabar deposits to be mined, but the demand for quicksilver soon skyrocketed. Because of its chemical affinity for gold and silver, mercury was of inestimable value in the refining process of precious metals and was needed throughout the United States, Mexico, and South America. Under the direction of Henry W. Halleck (later a general in the Civil War), the Mexican miners of New Almaden tunneled into the hillside to hammer and blast the cinnabar from the mine walls. Carried or pulled to the surface, tons of ore were roasted in huge furnaces to free the mercury. The silver liquid then passed through condensers into vats, from which it was carefully ladled into seventy-five pound flasks.
The miner's life at New Almaden was not an enviable one. Men worked ten to twelve hour shifts, six days a week, for wages of $1.50 to $2.50 a day. Deep, hard-rock mining in tunnels was dangerous enough in itself, but New Almaden miners had to contend with the highly poisonous mercurial fumes as well. Barron, Forbes showed little regard for the welfare of its employees. Medical care was virtually non-existent, and workers lived in squalid conditions, their hastily built shacks dotting the hillside of what became known as Spanishtown.
Barron, Forbes ran New Almaden at great profit and with no interruption for a decade. But the success of the venture began to attract others who endeavored to share in the bounty. Questions soon arose regarding the legality of the original Castillero claim as well as the subsequent transfer of shares to Barron, Forbes. The complexity of sorting out Mexican land titles in what was now United States land compounded the problem. A claim presented to the Board of Land Commissioners by Barron, Forbes in 1852 proved unsatisfactory, and a suit disputing the ownership of the mine was filed. A court injunction in 1858 forced Barron, Forbes to shut down operations while investigation and litigation continued. In 1863, the case reached the United States Supreme Court, where it was decided in a four to three decision that the title did not belong to Barron, Forbes.
Seizing the opportunity, the Quicksilver Mining Company made ready to take over the property. This firm, of Pennsylvania and New York, was formed solely in anticipation of a favorable Supreme Court ruling; once that ruling was handed down, the company quickly prepared for the takeover. Barron, Forbes attempted to resit the court decision--armed confrontations at the mine entrance between men from the Quicksilver Mining Company and miners for Barron, Forbes nearly resulted in bloodshed. President Abraham Lincoln entered the fray by issuing a writ supporting the federal seizure of the mine and equipment, but the public outcry over the arbitrary use of executive authority forced the President to back down. A settlement was eventually reached in 1864 that enabled the Quicksilver Mining Company to gain possession of New Almaden on payment of $1,750,000.
Under the Quicksilver Mining Company, little time was lost in resuming operations. Samuel Butterworth resigned as president of the company to become general manager of the mine (at an annual salary of $25,000). Under his able direction, the mine boomed; New Almaden produced more quicksilver in 1865 than the fabled Almaden in Spain, the world's greatest mercury mine. Gross income for the three year period 1864-1867 totaled some $6,000,000. Over one thousand men, mostly Cornish and Mexican immigrants, were on the company payroll.
Butterworth brought routine and rigid order to New Almaden where none had existed before. Mine property was declared private, and a toll gate was erected at the entrance. Improvements in mining operations were initiated, machinery was improved, and the processing became more sophisticated. A tramway was constructed that brought ore from the shafts to the furnaces. Mine superintendants maintained a tightly controlled daily routine. Cornish Cousin Jack and Mexican minero often labored alongside one another by day, but separated at quitting time--one returning home to Englishtown, the other to Spanishtown.
Samuel Butterworth resigned in 1870 and his nephew, James B. Randol, became general manager. Randol's long tenure of twenty-two years resembled that of his uncle in many ways. The company expected discipline, order, and hard work from its employees; they in turn received benefits that the company extended. Mine workers lived in company houses, relaxed at company recreation halls or company-sponsored social events, and spent their $40 to $100 a month at the Derby and Lowe company store. Those who paid one dollar a month to the Miners' Fund, New Almaden's health plan, received medical care from the company physician.
The mine continued to yield huge amounts of ore during Randol's years as manager. Newly-designed furnaces roared around the clock, reducing 154 tons of ore every twenty-four hours. By the early 1890s however, the glory days of quicksilver production in New Almaden were over. The mountain of cinnabar that lay beneath the cave Castillero had discovered was nearly depleted. The company cut back on employees and reduced operations. The 1893 depression forced even further cutbacks, and by 1912, the Quicksilver Mining Company had filed for and been granted bankruptcy.
Sporadic attempts to resume even small scale mining at New Almaden occurred throughout the first half of the twentieth century. Rising price and demand for mercury, especially during the war years, attracted many firms to the abandoned equipment and buildings atop Mine Hill as late as the 1950s. Production was limited, however, and each new venture lasted only a few years at most. During World War II, the mine was kept open and running on government orders, even though it was operating at a loss.
Today, the remains of the New Almaden repose quietly in the Capitancillos hills. The mine is protected from any land development by virtue of its Department of the Interior status as an historic landmark. Recent restorations of houses for viewing by the public and the opening of a museum signal the opening of a new era for New Almaden as a public park.
Series Description
- I Correspondence, 1853-1945 (Box 1-41)
  - External/President and New York Office, 1873-1944 (Box 1-4)
  - External/Manager and New Almaden Office, 1864-1928 (Box 5-22)
  - Internal/President, New York, and San Francisco Office, 1867-1929 (Box 23-27)
  - Internal/Manager and New Almaden Office, 1864-1943 (Box 28-33)
  - Internal/Superintendent, 1864-1911 (Box 34-41)
- II Corporate Records, 1864-1927 (Box 41-49)
  - Confidence Gold Mines Corporation, 1919 (Box 41)
  - Eureka Company, 1894-1909 (Box 41)
  - Guadalupe Mining Company, 1888 (Box 41)
  - New Almaden Company Incorporated, 1916-1925 (Box 41-42)
  - New Almaden Corporation, 1940-1946 (Box 42)
  - New Almaden Quicksilver Mines Corporation, 1916-1926 (Box 42)
  - New Almaden Stores, Incorporated, 1915-1926 (Box 42)
  - Quicksilver Investment Company, Incorporated, 1915-1916 (Box 42)
  - Quicksilver Mining Company, 1864-1923 (Box 42-49)
- III Mine Operations and Production, 1850-1960 (Box 50-79)
  - Reports to the Manager, 1865-1955 (Box 50-57)
  - Production Statistics, 1850-1958 (Box 57-59)
  - Assaying, 1867-1943 (Box 59-60)
  - Surveying, 1859-1944 (Box 60-68)
  - Mine Work/Machinery and Supplies, 1875-1960 (Box 68-70)
  - Mine Work/Progress Reports, 1860-1945 (Box 70-74)
  - Furnace Operations, 1877-1923 (Box 74-75)
  - Railroads, 1878-1942 (Box 75-76)
  - Miscellaneous, 1851-1945 (Box 76-79)
- IV Legal Documents, 1846-1945 (Box 79-84)
  - General, 1853-1945 (Box 79-80)
  - Litigation, 1850-1927 (Box 80-82)
  - Patents, 1864-1887 (Box 82-83)
  - Real Estate, 1846-1915 (Box 83-84)
- V Financial Records, 1851-1942 (Box 85-93)
  - Eureka Company, 1894-1910 (Box 85-87)
  - New Almaden Company Incorporated, 1915-1925 (Box 87-89)
  - New Almaden Company Incorporated/New Almaden Stores Incorporated, 1915-1924 (Box 89)
  - New Almaden Corporation, 1940-1941 (Box 89)
  - New Almaden Quicksilver Mines Corporation, 1916-1924 (Box 90)
  - New Almaden Stores Incorporated, 1915-1922 (Box 90)
  - Quicksilver Investment Company, 1915-1924 (Box 90)
  - Quicksilver Mining Company, 1851-1921 (Box 90-93)
- VI Employee Papers, 1848-1945 (Box 94-103)
  - Health and Workmen's Compensation, 1889-1945 (Box 94)
  - Payroll Records, 1881-1924 (Box 94-98)
  - Time Sheets, 1883-1945 (Box 98-102)
  - Miscellaneous, 1848-1944 (Box 102-103)
- VII Maps and Plans, 1841-1974 (Box 104)
  - Oversize map books
  - Buildings, 1879-1942 (Folder Map Folder 1-3)
  - Plats, 1841-1871 (Folder 3-4)
  - Machinery, 1876-1969 (Folder 4-11)
  - Ore Bins, 1879-1970 (Folder 11-13)
  - Furnaces, 1873-1917 (Folder 13-31)
  - Central Stope, 1864-1967 (Folder 31-34)
  - Harry, Santa Mariana, Velasco, Victoria, 1876-1969 (Folder 34-35)
  - Cora Blanca, 1872-1943 (Folder 35-37)
  - San Francisco, 1874-1968 (Folder 37-39)
  - San Pedro, Almaden, 1875-1970 (Folder 39-41)
  - North Randol, 1870-1890 (Folder 41-42)
  - South Randol, 1877-1969 (Folder 43-45)
  - America, 1868-1969 (Folder 45-46)
  - Providence-Enriquita, 1889-1966 (Folder 46-48)
  - San Antonio, Guadalupe, Outside Mines, 1875-1962 (Folder 48-49)
  - San Mateo, 1874-1966 (Folder 49-50)
  - Senator, 1916-1935 (Folder 50-51)
  - General, New Almaden, 1856-1971 (Folder 51-56)
  - Railroads, 1886-1910 (Folder 56-57)
  - Geology, 1935-1962 (Folder 57-60)
  - Level Sheets, 1935-1969 (Folder 60-63)
  - Topographical, 1879-1968 (Folder 63-69)
  - Surface Feature Maps, 1875-1969 (Folder 69-72)
  - Local/Area Maps, 1873 (Folder 73)
  - Tunnel Plans, 1858-1941 (Folder 73-87)
  - Unidentified (Folder 88)
  - Damaged (Folder 89-92)
  - Rolled Maps, 1856-1974
  - Glass Diorama
- VIII Research Notes, 1933-1968 (Box 105-111)
- IX Publications & Printed Material, 1843-1977 (Box 112-116)
  - Monographs and Published Material, 1859-1977 (Box 112-116)
  - Newsclippings, 1843-1970 (Box 116)
  - Printed Flyers, 1856-1953 (Box 116)
- X Photographs (Box 117-121)
  - Prints (Box 117-120)
  - Notes (Box 120)
  - Negatives, Glass (Othertype Oversize Shelving)
  - Negatives, Film (Othertype 121, Nitrate Shelving)
Container List
- SERIES I: CORRESPONDENCE, 1853-1945
  - EXTERNAL
    - PRESIDENT AND NEW YORK OFFICE
      - OUTGOING
        - 1882-1902,letterpress (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - 1904-1910,letterpress (Box 1, Folder 2)
        - 1915,letterpress (Box 2, Folder 1)
        - 1918-1919,letterpress (Box 2, Folder 2)
        - 1919,letterpress (Box 2, Folder 3)
        - 1940-1942,re: Kilmartin (Box 2, Folder 4)
        - 1940-1943,re: Ammerman's drafting (Box 2, Folder 5)
        - 1940-1943,re: wage scales (Box 2, Folder 6)
        - 1940-1944,re: selling (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - INCOMING
        - 1873 (Box 3, Folder 1)
        - 1874-1875 (Box 3, Folder 2)
        - 1876 (Box 3, Folder 3)
        - 1876-1880,re: patents (Box 3, Folder 4)
        - 1877 (Box 3, Folder 5)
        - 1878 (Box 3, Folder 6)
        - 1879 (Box 3, Folder 7)
        - 1880 (Box 3, Folder 8)
        - 1881 (Box 3, Folder 9)
        - 1901-1908 (Box 3, Folder 10)
        - 1909 (Box 3, Folder 11)
        - 1910 (Box 3, Folder 12)
        - 1911 (Box 3, Folder 13)
        - Jan.-June 1912 (Box 3, Folder 14)
        - July-Dec. 1912 (Box 3, Folder 15)
        - 1913 (Box 4, Folder 1)
        - 1915 (Box 4, Folder 2)
        - Jan.-June 1916 (Box 4, Folder 3)
        - July-Dec. 1916 (Box 4, Folder 4)
        - Jan.-Feb. 1917 (Box 4, Folder 5)
        - Mar.-June 1917 (Box 4, Folder 6)
        - July-Dec. 1917 (Box 4, Folder 7)
        - Jan.-June 1918 (Box 4, Folder 8)
        - July-Dec. 1918 (Box 4, Folder 9)
        - Jan.-June 1919 (Box 4, Folder 10)
        - July-Dec. 1919 (Box 4, Folder 11)
        - 1920 (Box 4, Folder 12)
        - 1921 (Box 4, Folder 13)
        - Jan.-Mar. 1922 (Box 4, Folder 14)
        - Apr.-Sept. 1922 (Box 4, Folder 15)
        - Oct.-Dec. 1922 (Box 4, Folder 16)
        - 1940-1942,re: Ammerman's drafting (Box 4, Folder 17)
        - 1940-1943,re: Knight, Boland, and Riordan (Attorneys) (Box 4, Folder 18)
        - 1940-May 1942,re: Uhe (Foreign accounts agent) (Box 4, Folder 19)
        - June-Dec. 1942,re: Uhe (Box 4, Folder 20)
        - Jan.-Aug. 1943,re: Uhe (Box 4, Folder 21)
        - Sept. 1943-Dec. 1945.re: Uhe (Box 4, Folder 22)
        - N.d.,memo re: Boards of Directors (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - MANAGER AND NEW ALMADEN OFFICE
      - OUTGOING
        - 1864-1867,letterpress (Box 5, Folder 1)
        - 1864-1868,foreign agents, letterpress (Box 5, Folder 2)
        - 1867-1871,letterpress (Box 5, Folder 3)
        - 1867-1870,letterpress, to superintendent (Box 6, Folder 1)
        - May 1871-Nov. 12, 1872,letterpress (Box 6, Folder 2)
        - Nov. 14, 1872-Mar. 14, 1874,letterpress (Box 6, Folder 3)
        - Oct. 31, 1874-June 10, 1875,letterpress (Box 6, Folder 4)
        - June 11, 1875-Feb. 10, 1876,letterpress (Box 7, Folder 1)
        - Sept. 27, 1876-May 21, 1877,letterpress (Box 7, Folder 2)
        - May 21-Dec. 7, 1877,letterpress (Box 7, Folder 3)
        - May 23-Oct. 9, 1878,letterpress (Box 8, Folder 1)
        - Oct. 9, 1878-Apr. 13, 1879,letterpress (Box 8, Folder 2)
        - Apr. 14-Nov. 17, 1879,letterpress (Box 8, Folder 3)
        - Nov. 17, 1879-Apr. 2, 1881,letterpress (Box 9, Folder 1)
        - Apr. 4, 1881-June 12, 1882,letterpress (Box 9, Folder 2)
        - June 13-Dec. 1882,letterpress (Box 9, Folder 3)
        - 1864-1866 (Box 10, Folder 1)
        - 1870-1879 (Box 10, Folder 2)
        - 1880-1889 (Box 10, Folder 3)
        - 1890-1909 (Box 10, Folder 4)
        - 1910 (Box 10, Folder 5)
        - 1911 (Box 10, Folder 6)
        - 1912 (Box 10, Folder 7)
        - 1913 (Box 10, Folder 8)
        - 1914 (Box 10, Folder 9)
        - 1915 (Box 10, Folder 10)
        - 1916 (Box 10, Folder 11)
        - 1917 (Box 10, Folder 12)
        - 1918 (Box 10, Folder 13)
        - 1919 (Box 10, Folder 14)
        - 1920 (Box 10, Folder 15)
        - 1921-1922 (Box 10, Folder 16)
        - 1923 (Box 10, Folder 17)
        - 1924-1926 (Box 10, Folder 18)
      - INCOMING
        - 1853-1866 (Box 11, Folder 1)
        - 1865-1866 (Box 11, Folder 2)
        - 1866-1867,foreign (Box 11, Folder 3)
        - 1867 (Box 11, Folder 4)
        - 1867-1868,telegrams (Box 11, Folder 5)
        - 1868 (Box 11, Folder 6)
        - Jan.-July, 1869 (Box 11, Folder 7)
        - Aug.-Dec. 1869 (Box 11, Folder 8)
        - Jan.-Apr. 1870 (Box 11, Folder 9)
        - May-Aug. 1870 (Box 11, Folder 10)
        - Sept.-Dec. 1870 (Box 12, Folder 1)
        - Jan.-Apr. 1871 (Box 12, Folder 2)
        - May-June, 1871 (Box 12, Folder 3)
        - July-Sept. 1871 (Box 12, Folder 4)
        - Oct.-Dec. 1871 (Box 12, Folder 5)
        - Jan.-Mar. 1872 (Box 12, Folder 6)
        - Apr.-Dec. 1872 (Box 12, Folder 7)
        - Jan.-June 1873 (Box 12, Folder 8)
        - July-Sept. 1873 (Box 12, Folder 9)
        - Oct.-Dec. 1873 (Box 12, Folder 10)
        - Jan.-Feb. 1874 (Box 13, Folder 1)
        - Mar.-Apr. 1874 (Box 13, Folder 2)
        - May-June 1874 (Box 13, Folder 3)
        - July 1874 (Box 13, Folder 4)
        - Aug. 1874 (Box 13, Folder 5)
        - Sept. 1874 (Box 13, Folder 6)
        - Oct. 1874 (Box 13, Folder 7)
        - Nov. 1874 (Box 13, Folder 8)
        - Dec. 1874 (Box 14, Folder 1)
        - Jan. 1875 (Box 14, Folder 2)
        - Feb. 1875 (Box 14, Folder 3)
        - Mar. 1875 (Box 14, Folder 4)
        - Apr. 1875 (Box 14, Folder 5)
        - May-June 1875 (Box 14, Folder 6)
        - July 1875 (Box 14, Folder 7)
        - Aug. 1875 (Box 15, Folder 1)
        - Sept. 1875 (Box 15, Folder 2)
        - Oct. 1875 (Box 15, Folder 3)
        - Nov. 1875 (Box 15, Folder 4)
        - Dec. 1875 (Box 15, Folder 5)
        - Jan. 1876 (Box 15, Folder 6)
        - Feb. 1876 (Box 15, Folder 7)
        - Mar. 1876 (Box 15, Folder 8)
        - Apr.-May 1876 (Box 15, Folder 9)
        - Jun.-July 1876 (Box 15, Folder 10)
        - Jan.-Feb. 1877 (Box 15, Folder 11)
        - Mar. 1877 (Box 15, Folder 12)
        - Apr. 1877 (Box 15a, Folder 1)
        - May 1877 (Box 15a, Folder 2)
        - June 1877 (Box 15a, Folder 3)
        - July 1877 (Box 15a, Folder 4)
        - Aug. 1877 (Box 15a, Folder 5)
        - Sept.-Oct. 1877 (Box 15a, Folder 6)
        - Nov. 1877 (Box 16, Folder 1)
        - Dec. 1877 (Box 16, Folder 2)
        - Jan. 1878 (Box 16, Folder 3)
        - Feb. 1878 (Box 16, Folder 4)
        - Mar. 1878 (Box 16, Folder 5)
        - Apr. 1878 (Box 16, Folder 6)
        - May 1878 (Box 16, Folder 7)
        - June 1878 (Box 16, Folder 8)
        - July 1878 (Box 16, Folder 9)
        - Aug. 1878 (Box 16, Folder 10)
        - Sept. 1878 (Box 17, Folder 1)
        - Oct. 1878 (Box 17, Folder 2)
        - Nov. 1878-Sept. 1879 (Box 17, Folder 3)
        - Oct. 1879 (Box 17, Folder 4)
        - Nov. 1879 (Box 17, Folder 5)
        - Dec. 1879 (Box 17, Folder 6)
        - Jan.-Feb. 1880 (Box 17, Folder 7)
        - Mar.-Apr. 1880 (Box 17, Folder 8)
        - May-June 1880 (Box 18, Folder 1)
        - July-Aug. 1880 (Box 18, Folder 2)
        - Sept.-Oct. 1880 (Box 18, Folder 3)
        - Nov.-Dec. 1880 (Box 18, Folder 4)
        - Jan.-Mar. 1881 (Box 18, Folder 5)
        - Apr.-June 1881 (Box 18, Folder 6)
        - July-Sept. 1881 (Box 18, Folder 7)
        - Oct.-Nov. 1881 (Box 18, Folder 8)
        - Dec. 1881-Mar. 1882 (Box 19, Folder 1)
        - Apr. 1882 (Box 19, Folder 2)
        - May-June 1882 (Box 19, Folder 3)
        - July 1882 (Box 19, Folder 4)
        - Aug.-Sept. 1882 (Box 19, Folder 5)
        - Oct. 1882 (Box 19, Folder 6)
        - Nov.-Dec. 1882 (Box 19, Folder 7)
        - 1882,[attached] (Box 19, Folder 8)
        - Jan.-Feb. 1883 (Box 19, Folder 9)
        - Mar. 1883 (Box 19, Folder 10)
        - Apr.-May 1883 (Box 19, Folder 11)
        - June-Dec. 1883 (Box 19, Folder 12)
        - Jan.-May 1884 (Box 19, Folder 13)
        - June-Aug. 1884 (Box 19, Folder 14)
        - Sept.-Dec. 1884 (Box 19, Folder 15)
        - Jan.-Mar. 1885 (Box 20, Folder 1)
        - Apr.-June 1885 (Box 20, Folder 2)
        - July-Sept. 1885 (Box 20, Folder 3)
        - Oct.-Dec. 1885 (Box 20, Folder 4)
        - 1885 (Box 20, Folder 5)
        - Jan.-June 1886 (Box 20, Folder 6)
        - July-Dec. 1886 (Box 20, Folder 7)
        - Jan.-Mar. 1887 (Box 20, Folder 8)
        - Apr.-June 1887 (Box 20, Folder 9)
        - July-Sept. 1887 (Box 20, Folder 10)
        - Oct.-Dec. 1887 (Box 20, Folder 11)
        - 1888 (Box 20, Folder 12)
        - 1889 (Box 21, Folder 1)
        - 1890 (Box 21, Folder 2)
        - 1891 (Box 21, Folder 3)
        - 1892 (Box 21, Folder 4)
        - 1893 (Box 21, Folder 5)
        - 1894-1897 (Box 21, Folder 6)
        - 1914 (Box 21, Folder 7)
        - 1915 (Box 21, Folder 8)
        - Jan.-June 1916 (Box 21, Folder 9)
        - July-Dec. 1916 (Box 21, Folder 10)
        - Jan.-Feb. 1917 (Box 21, Folder 11)
        - Mar.-June 1917 (Box 21, Folder 12)
        - July-Dec. 1917 (Box 21, Folder 13)
        - Jan.-June 1918 (Box 21, Folder 14)
        - July-Dec. 1918 (Box 21, Folder 15)
        - Jan.-June 1919 (Box 22, Folder 1)
        - July-Dec. 1919 (Box 22, Folder 2)
        - 1920 (Box 22, Folder 3)
        - 1921 (Box 22, Folder 4)
        - Jan.-Mar. 1922 (Box 22, Folder 5)
        - Apr.-Sept. 1922 (Box 22, Folder 6)
        - Oct.-Dec. 1922 (Box 22, Folder 7)
        - Jan.-Feb. 1923 (Box 22, Folder 8)
        - Mar.-May 1923 (Box 22, Folder 9)
        - June-Aug. 1923 (Box 22, Folder 10)
        - Sept.-Dec. 1923 (Box 22, Folder 11)
        - Jan.-Apr. 1924 (Box 22, Folder 12)
        - May-Sept. 1924 (Box 22, Folder 13)
        - Oct.-Dec. 1924 (Box 22, Folder 14)
        - 1925-1928 (Box 22, Folder 15)
        - 1940 (Box 22, Folder 16)
  - INTERNAL
    - PRESIDENT, NEW YORK, AND SAN FRANCISCO OFFICE
      - OUTGOING
        - 1867-1876,telegrams, letterpress (Box 23, Folder 1)
        - 1882-1888,letterpress (Box 23, Folder 2)
        - 1895-1905,letterpress (Box 23, Folder 3)
        - 1910 (Box 23, Folder 4)
        - 1910-1912,letterpress (Box 24, Folder 1)
        - 1915-1918,telegrams, letterpress (Box 24, Folder 2)
      - INCOMING
        - 1867 (Box 24, Folder 3)
        - 1868 (Box 24, Folder 4)
        - 1869 (Box 24, Folder 5)
        - 1870 (Box 24, Folder 6)
        - 1871 (Box 25, Folder 1)
        - 1872 (Box 25, Folder 2)
        - 1873 (Box 25, Folder 3)
        - 1874,Engineer to New York (Box 25, Folder 4)
        - 1874 (Box 25, Folder 5)
        - 1875 (Box 25, Folder 6)
        - Jan.-June 1876 (Box 25, Folder 7)
        - July-Dec. 1876 (Box 25, Folder 8)
        - 1877 (Box 25, Folder 9)
        - 1878 (Box 25, Folder 10)
        - Jan.-July 1879 (Box 26, Folder 1)
        - Aug.-Dec. 1879 (Box 26, Folder 2)
        - 1880 (Box 26, Folder 3)
        - 1881 (Box 26, Folder 4)
        - 1882 (Box 26, Folder 5)
        - 1883 (Box 26, Folder 6)
        - 1884 (Box 26, Folder 7)
        - 1885 (Box 26, Folder 8)
        - 1886 (Box 26, Folder 9)
        - 1887 (Box 26, Folder 10)
        - 1889 (Box 26, Folder 11)
        - 1890 (Box 26, Folder 12)
        - 1891 (Box 26, Folder 13)
        - 1891-1898,Accountant to New York (Box 26, Folder 14)
        - 1910 (Box 27, Folder 1)
        - 1911 (Box 27, Folder 2)
        - 1911,telegrams (Box 27, Folder 3)
        - 1912 (Box 27, Folder 4)
        - 1912,unsigned, New Almaden Office to New York Office (Box 27, Folder 5)
        - 1913 (Box 27, Folder 6)
        - 1914 (Box 27, Folder 7)
        - Jan.-June 1915 (Box 27, Folder 8)
        - July-Aug. 1915 (Box 27, Folder 9)
        - Sept.-Dec. 1915 (Box 27, Folder 10)
        - 1916,Engineer to President (Box 27, Folder 11)
        - 1916-1917 (Box 27, Folder 12)